American Philosophical Society Archives 1743-1984 APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
Chapman, Nathaniel. Letter to the Committee of the American Philosophical Society. 1836 October 17. Report on medicine relating to the United States Exploring Expedition. Enclosed in Committee of the American Philosophical Society to [Mahlon Dickerson]. 1 page.
Committee of the American Philosophical Society. Letter to [Mahlon Dickerson]. 1836 October 17. With regard to the scientific methods and objectives of the United States Exploring Expedition, also known as the Wilkes Expedition. 9 pages.
Committee of the American Philosophical Society. Letter to Mahlon Dickerson. 1836 October 17. Enclosed anonymous list of books recommended for the officers and scientific corps, United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Committee of the American Philosophical Society. Letter to Mahlon Dickerson. 1836 October. Regarding the scientific methods and objectives of the United States Exploring Expedition, also known as the Wilkes Expedition. 32 pages.
Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. 1836 October 17. Report on ethnography, relating to the United States Exploring Expedition. Enclosed in Committee of A.P.S. to [Mahlon Dickerson]. 1 page.
Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. 1836 October 17. Report on philology, relating to the United States Exploring Expedition. Enclosed in Committee of A.P.S. to [Mahlon Dickerson]. 6 pages.
Espy, James P. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. Report on meteorology, related to the United States Exploring Expedition. Enclosed in Committee of the American Philosophical Society to [Mahlon Dickerson]. 12 pages.
Patterson, Robert M. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. Report upon astronomical and physical observations, related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 7 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. Report on zoology, related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
Pickering, Charles. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. Report upon botany, related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Rogers, Henry D. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. List of works which the geologists will find it useful to take with them. Related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Rogers, Henry D. Letter to Committee of the American Philosophical Society. n.d. [submitted 1836 October 17]. Report upon geology and mineralogy, related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 5 pages.
Dickerson, Mahlon. Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau. 1836 November 19. Acknowledges receipt of communication upon the South Sea Exploring Expedition (the United States Exploring Expedition). "It will form the basis of the Instructions to the scientific corps..." 1 page.
Coates, Reynell. Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau. 1837 August 28. Transmits the thanks of the scientific corps of the United States Exploring Expedition for "the completion of the name of books required for the...Expedition." 1 page.
Dickerson, Mahlon. Letter to Peter S. Du Ponceau. 1837 September 11. Returns thanks for report of the 2nd, in regards to the South Sea Exploring Expedition (the United States Exploring Expedition). 1 page.
Warrington, L. Letter to Colonel J. J. Abert. 1841 October 9. Returns thanks for information furnished by John Vaughan concerning charts of the Pacific Ocean in his possession. Related to the United States Exploring Expedition. 1 page.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to Alexander Dallas Bache and John Ludlow. 1843 May 8. Important part played by the American Philosophical Society regarding the organization of scientific corps of the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Letter to the Joint Library Committee of Congress. 1846 February 4. Requesting larger edition of scientific reports of the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
Gray, Asa. Letter to the Secretary of the American Philosophical Society. 1846 February 8. Encloses copy of letter from the American Academy of Arts and Sciences to the joint library committee of Congress asking for the publication of a larger edition of the scientific reports of the United States Exploring Expedition. 2 pages.
New York Historical Society. Letter to the Corresponding Secretary of the American Philosophical Society. 1847 February 26. Letter transmitting resolutions asking Congress to authorize a larger edition of the scientific volumes of the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
United States. Navy.
Kennedy, John Pendleton. Letter to Robley Dunglison. 1853 January 2. Thanking American Philosophical Society resolutions approving the U.S. Navy Department's scientific exploration, and Dr. Kane's joining of the Arctic expedition. 3 pages.
United States, Department of the Navy. Letter to Boies Penrose. 1899 January 25. Concerning copy of Battles and Capitulation of Santiago de Cuba for the American Philosophical Society Library. 1 page.
United States, Department of the Navy. Letter to Boies Penrose. 1899 September 14. Concerning astronomical documents for the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
United States, Department of the Navy. Letter to Boies Penrose. 1899 September 20. Sends copy of Stockton's Preparation for War requested for the American Philosophical Society Library. 1 page.
United States Naval Academy.
Chauvenet, William. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1856 May 28. U.S. Naval Academy librarian inquiring as to the availability of a complete set of the American Philosophical Society Transactions. 1 page.
Chauvenet, William. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1856 July 10. Ordering a complete set of the American Philosophical Society Transactions for the U.S. Naval Academy Library. 1 page.
Chauvenet, William. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1856 September 29. Requesting the American Philosophical Society Transactions be sent to the U.S. Naval Academy Library. 1 page.
Doran, Edward. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1856 October 28. Regarding the U.S. Naval Academy's outstanding account with the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
United States Naval Observatory.
Gilliss, J. M. Letter to Charles B. Trego. 1861 December 24. Requesting Proceedings and Transactions of the American Philosophical Society. 2 pages.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to J. P. Lesley. 1862 January 21. Concerning package of books, and American Philosophical Society publications. 1 page.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to J. P. Lesley. 1862 January 21. Thanking for American Philosophical Society Proceedings and Transactions. 1 page.
Sands, B. F. Letter to President of the American Philosophical Society. 1872 January 30. Concerning material to be presented to Congress to facilitate observation of the transit of Venus. 4 pages.
Graham, James D. Letter to J. P. Lesley. 1872 February 29. Acknowledging receipt of memorial on the American Philosophical Society to Congress on the transit of Venus. 2 pages.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to J. P. Lesley. 1874 May 30. Forwarding the American Philosophical Society's Proceedings to Admiral Charles Wilkes. Offers pamphlet (lacking). 1 page.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to the Secretary of the American Philosophical Society. 1876 February 15. Letter to J. P. Lesley concerning the American Philosophical Society's promotion of the Polaris expedition. 2 pages.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to the Librarian of the American Philosophical Society. 1877 January 31. Forwards publications. 1 page.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to the American Philosophical Society. 1898 February 7. Cannot supply a publication to the American Philosophical Society Library, refers to hydrographic office, Boies Penrose. 1 page.
United States Naval Observatory. Letter to Isaac Minis Hays. 1899 April 11. Concerning the publications of the U.S. Naval Observatory needed by the American Philsophical Society Library. 1 page.
United States. Naval War Records Office.
United States, Naval War Records Office. Letter to Boies Penrose. 1898 November 9. Concerning copy of "Office Memoranda No. 8. Officers of the Confederate States Navy" requested for the American Philosophical Society Library. 1 page.
Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877.
Anonymous. List of instruments procured by Lieutenant Wilkes for the Exploring Expedition. 1837. Manuscript. 2 pages.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to Alexander Dallas Bache and John Ludlow. 1843 May 6. Hopes to attend the American Philosophical Society centennial celebration, but will not have time to prepare a paper on the United States Exploring Expedition. 3 pages.
Peale, Titian Ramsay. Letter to George Ord. 1845 February 11. Inquires as to location of certain rare botanical works. "Captain Wilkes is now in Philadelphia..." 2 pages.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to George Ord. 1845 May 23. Presents a copy of his Narrative of the Exploring Expedition to the American Philosophical Society. 1 page.
Wilkes, Charles. Letter to the President of the American Philosophical Society. 1857 August 22. Forwarding a publication. 1 page.
African American History Note
The APS archives does not contain a tremendous amount of African American history materials. Nevertheless, the following letter is significant:
Dearborn, Benjamin. Letter to the American Philosophical Society. 1803 February 4. Suggestions on the abolition of slavery.
Early American History Note
The APS Archives contain a wide range of material on early American history. MOLE contains a detailed breakdown of its content.
Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Bache, Franklin, 1792-1864; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815; Bartram, Moses, d. 1791; Bell, Whitfield J. (Whitfield Jenks); Brown, Samuel, 1768-1805; Churchman, John, 1753-1805; Conklin, Edwin Grant, 1863-1952; Dercum, Francis X., (Francis Xavier), 1856-1931; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Du Pont de Nemours, Pierre Samuel, 1739-1817; Dunbar, William, 1749-1810; Ellicott, Andrew, 1754-1820; Evans, Oliver, 1755-1819; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Hanson, Laura E.; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843; Hassler, F. R, (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843; Hays, I. Minis, (Isaac Minis), 1847-1925; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Keen, William W., (William Williams), b. 1837; Latrobe, Benjamin Henry, 1764-1820; Legaux, Peter,1748-1827.; Lingelbach, William E., (William Ezra), 1871-1962; Logan, George, 1753-1821; Long, Stephen Harriman, 1784-1864; Matlack, Timothy, 1736-1829; Morris, Roland Sletor, 1874-1945; Nicola, Lewis, 1717-1807; Page, John, 1744-1808; Patterson,, Robert M., (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854; Patterson, Robert, 1743-1824; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851; Priestly, Joseph R.; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796; Rumsey, James, 1743?-1792; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834; Scott, William B. (President, 1918-1925); Shryock, Richard Harrison, 1893-1972; Silliman, Benjamin, Sr., 1779-1864; Thornton, William, 1759-1828; Valltravers, Johann Rodolph; Varle, Charles; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Warden, David Baillie, 1772-1845; Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818; Wood, George Bacon, 1797-1879; Abolition, emancipation, freedom; African American; American Philosophical Society; Astronomy--18th century; Colonial Politics; Early National Politics; Education; History of science and technology.; Indians of North America--Northwest Coast; Institutional Records; Miscellaneous; Native America; Native American Materials; Natural History; Natural History--18th century; Natural History--19th century; Pencil works; Pennsylvania History; Philadelphia History; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; United States History.
- Minutes and By-Laws, 1758-1971; I; 7.0 ln. ft.
  Scope and Contents note
  The Archives contains minutes of both the American Society and the American Philosophical Society, which united in 1769 to form the American Philosophical Society, held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. The records of the first-named give its title variously as American Society for Promoting and Propagating Useful Knowledge, held at Philadelphia; and American Society held at Philadelphia for Promoting Useful Knowledge. For convenience, it is referred to here as the American Society. In addition, the Archives has minutes of a predecessor of the American Society, which was sometimes called the "Young Junto," but is here identified by the binder's title as the "Junto."
  - Junto. Minutes, 1758-1762; I.1; 1.0 vol. (101 pp.)
  - American Society. Minutes, 1758-1768; I.2; 1.0 vol. (163 pp.)
  - American Society. Rules and statutes, ca. 1768; I.3; 1.0 vol. (11 pp.)
  - American Philosophical Society. Minutes, 1768; I.4; 1.0 vol. (38 pp.)
    Contains the signatures of members under each of the six standing committees.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Minutes, 1769-; I.5; 19.0 vol.
    Volumes to 1932 are in the Library. The minutes of 1768-1837 have been abstracted by Henry Phillips, Jr., in "Early proceedings of the American Philosophical Society ... 1744 to 1838," in APS Proceedings 22, 3 (1885). Beginning in 1838 abstracts were printed in the current APS Proceedings until 1937, since which date they have appeared in the Year Book.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Rough minutes, 1771-1804, 1819-1927; I.6; 40.0 vol.
    In particular instances the rough minutes are fuller than the minutes as finally transcribed. After about 1900 the principal articles in the minutes were prepared in advance of meetings. The first volume contains a few original reports of committees appointed to examine certain scientific undertakings proposed by individuals to the Society.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Laws and regulations, 1804; I.7; 1.0 vol. (42 pp.)
    A formal record, required by the by-laws of 1804, of the Fundamental Laws of 1769; the Act of Incorporation of 1780; the Act of Assembly of 1785, with supplements, granting the Society a piece of State-House Square; the conditions of the award of the Magellanic Premium; and the by-laws adopted May 4, 1804. Also included is a list of members of various committees.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Amendments to Laws, 1928-1971; I.8; 11.0 items
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Standing orders, 1885-1925; I.9; 1.0 vol. (57 pp.)
    A compilation from the minutes of orders, or procedures covering the operations of the Society.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Minutes, 1838-1871; I.10; Index. ca. 3500 cards
    Card file index prepared by Associate Librarian Murphy D. Smith during the 1960s.
  - American Philosophical Society, Held at Philadelphia, for Promoting Useful Knowledge. Charter of the American Philosophical Society, ..., 1780; I.11; 2.0 items
    A copy of the act for incorporation the Society. There is also a printed version included
- "Archives", 1743-1984; II.1; 28.0 ln. ft.
  The collection contains every sort of material relating to the business of the Society, such as drafts of minutes, committee reports, letters of officers and others, memoranda, scientific papers and proposals, orders, receipts, and other material. The papers from 1797-1844 may be of particular interest to scholars of American Indian ethnology, history, and linguistics.
  Native American Images note: Four folders containing up to 275 pencil and ink sketches, from 1816-1840, of Cherokee, Choctaw, Adena, and Aztec native culture. Primarily of burial mounds located in Lexington, Kentucky; Grave Creek, West Virginia; and Washington, Mississippi. Of particular note, a printed pictograph of Boturini Codex depicting the Aztec journey from Aztlan to the Valley of Mexico. Also known as Tira de la Peregrinacion, it contains 22 pages in black ink on one sheet folded accordion style. Each folder is noted in APS Freeman Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian.
  Adena culture--West Virginia; Aztecs.; Cherokee Indians; Choctaw Indians; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Grave Creek Mound (Marshall County, West Virginia); Indians of Mexico; Indians of North America--Kentucky; Indians of North America--Mississippi; Indians of North America--West Virginia; Mound builders; Plains Indians; Southeast Indians
  - Joint petition to the General Assembly of Pennsylvania for two lots on State House Square., 1784; American Philosophical Society and Library Company of Philadelphia, joint petition to the General Assembly of Pennsylvania for two lots on State House Square.
  - Subscription list for the building of Philosophical Hall, 1785 July 11
  - Manuscript subscription list put forward by Jefferson to support a proposed scientific expedition under Andre Michaux, 1793., 1.0 Item(s); Subscription list with the autographs of the first four Presidents of the United States.
  - Navigation made easy, or a Mariners complete guide, May 2, 1800, 1.0 volume, 15 p.; Hoskins, Francis
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    This item is also available on microfilm (Film 199, Frame 755).
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Received and accessioned, 1800.
    Hoskins presents an idea for a new hourglass-type timepiece and a formula for calculating the longitude without the need for an expensive timepiece. He tested it on a voyage from Philadelphia to Cork, Ireland. The log of this journey is reproduced, and a chart is given as well.
    Dedicated to Thomas Jefferson, this treatise was submitted to the American Philosophical Society for a Magellanic Premium award in 1800 [see "Minutes," p. 299]. It was submitted anonymously, under the name of "Hiram," but a second, almost identical version (dated 1803) was received at the A.P.S. with Hoskin's name on it in 1839 [Misc. Ms. Coll.].
    - Chart of a voyage across the Atlantic Ocean from Philadelphia to Cork, Ireland, 1800; Map, 49.5 x 19.7 cm; Hoskins, Francis
      Other Finding Aids note
      Realms of Gold, 1 (1).
  - Sketch of the plan of an ancient work, three miles to the southeast of Lexington, 1816 August 31; Pencil sketch, 8 x 9 1/2"; Short, Charles Wilkins, 1794-1863
    Short's description was read on 4 October 1816 to the Society's members. It was published, with a small engraving of the drawing, in the American Philosophical Society Transactions, n.s., vol. 1: pp. 310-312, plate IX, fig. 3.
    Realms of Gold, 1 (2).
  - Symbolic account of the migration of the Aztec, 1827; Ink sketches, 18' 7" x 8"
    Freeman guide, 443
    - Codice Boturini, 1827
    - Codice Boturini, 1827
  - S. P. Hullihen to Richard Harlan, 1830 September 27; Ink sketch, 1 1/2 x 2"; Hullihen, S. P.
    Freeman guide, 1215
    Harlan, Richard
  - Great Indian mound near Washington, Adams County, Mississippi, 1840 September?; Ink sketch, 8 x 9 1/2"; Forshey, Caleb Goldsmith, 1812-1881
    Freeman guide, 1212. Realms of Gold, 1 (3).
- Communications, 1748-1837; III; 4.0 ln. ft.
  - Manuscript communications, 1748-1837; III.1; 3.5 ln. ft.
    A portion of the APS Archives, the Manuscript Communications (III.1) consists of letters and papers on a variety of topics sent to the APS between the 1770s and 1830s. Many of the papers were read at meetings of the Society, some were published in the APS Transactions, and others were submitted for consideration for the premiums offered by the APS for best paper on the topic of education.
    Once part of the general APS Archives, the Manuscript Communications were separated at an early date, arranged in chronological order, and bound into volumes under seven topical series:
    Mechanics, Machinery, and Engineering
    Trade, Navigation, Manufactures, Agriculture, Economics
    Medicine, Anatomy, Physiology
    Natural History
    Trade, Commerce, Navigation, Manufactures, Agriculture, Husbandry and Economics
    Natural Philosophy
    Mathematics and Astronomy
    - ALS to David Rittenhouse, 1795 June 19; 1.0 item; A.L.O.T.A. (pseud) (Box 1)
      Originally enclosed in ALOTA to David Rittenhouse, 1795 June 19
      Includes pen and ink sketches of ships pumps.
    - Concerning improvements in ship pumps, 1795 June 19; 5.0 items; A.L.O.T.A. (pseud) (Box 1)
    - ALS to Thomas Jefferson, 1797 Jan. 13; 1.0 item; Academicus (Box 1)
      A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Enc. Concerning education. For enclosure, see Academicus: Plan for the education of youth [circa Jan. 1797]. FILM199, FRAME 374
    - Plan for the education of youth, ca.1797 Jan.; 1.0 item; Academicus (Box 1)
      D. 29p. and end. Enclosed originally in letter from Academicus to [T. Jefferson]; January 13, 1797. FILM199, FRAME 374
    - Account of two parhelia (rainbows), 1756 Dec. 21; 1.0 item (Box OS)
      For account of this, see H. Williamson, 'Concerning parhelia rainbows,' 1816 May 20
    - ALS to the American Philosophical Society. Secretary, 1832 May 24; 1.0 item; Acosta, Joaquim (Box 1)
      For enclosure, see Jean Boussingault, Researches on the cause of goiter, 1830 Oct.
      Medicine, Anatomy, and Physiology
    - ALS to John Vaughan, 1810 June 12; 1.0 item; Adrain, Robert (Box 1)
    - Concerning a plan for exciting ambition in schools, 1813 Jan. 1; 1.0 item; Alden, Timothy (Box 1)
    - Hints for the American Philosophical Society, 1773 April 2; 1.0 item; Alison, Francis (Box 1)
      Regarding fences and a 'diligent attention to husbandry' and agriculture
      Printed: Phila. Soc. For Promoting Agriculture Memoirs 6, 127ff.
    - Concerning a pneumatometre rain gage and an improved anemoscope, 1801 Jan. 16; 3.0 items; Allison, Burgiss (Box 1)
      note; contains sketches of Anemoscope, Pneumatometre and Rain Gage
    - ALS to James Ewing, 1780 Nov. 20; 1.0 item; American Academy of Arts and Sciences. (Box 1)
      Enclosing J. Williard, Observations of the solar eclipse, 1780 Nv. 20, and AAAS, Catalogue of officers, 1780 Nov. 20
    - Catalogue of officers elected Aug. 30, 1780, 1780 Nov. 20; 1.0 item; American Academy of Arts and Sciences. (Box 1)
      Originally enclosed in AAAS to James Ewing, 1780 Nov. 20
    - ALS to I. Caffrey, 1797 June; 1.0 item; American Philosophical Society. (Box 1)
      Invitation to collect fossils for APS, including mention of mastodon and Megalonyx.
    - Concerning inquiries to be made by Major Long of the Indians, ca.1819 Mar. 30; 2.0 items; American Philosophical Society. (Box 1)
      Originally enclosed in Robert Walsh to John Caldwell Calhoun, 1819 March 30
      4 sets of queries by Peter S. DuPonceau, Dr. Samuel Brown, Dr. R. M. Patterson, and Robert Walsh, concerning: government, family, social organization, disease, origins, mental traits, virtues and vices, traditions, warfare, language, environment, horses, general character; origins and connections, manners and customs, language; specific diseases, incidence and treatment; childbirth and attendant medical phenomena.
      Freeman and Smith 1408
    - NS to Jared Mansfield, 1816 ca. Sept.; 1.0 item; American Philosophical Society. (Box 1)
    - Report of Committee on Hosack's paper on the communication of contagious diseases, 1812 Dec. 3; 1.0 item; American Philosophical Society. (Box 1)
      For paper see Hosack, David to Colin Chisholm, 1812 July 10
    - Report of Committee on J.J. Hawkins' Plan of a City, 1800 ca. Nov.; 1.0 item; American Philosophical Society. (Box 1)
      For paper reported on, See Hawkins, John J., Plan for Building a City, 1800, Sept. 19.